Guide to the Memory Project Oral History collection, 2009-2016 | 民间记忆计划口述史 RL.10171
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Hunan province | 湖南省, 2009-2016
  - Baiyun Xiang | 常德市石门县白云乡, 2010 and undated
    - Peng Gonge | 彭功娥, 2010
      彭功娥（1938年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡竹巷口村村民，王吉生妻子。在这段口述中，彭老人回忆兴办公社食堂时期，村民胡中焕偷食堂的米被村干部毒打。李未出嫁时，全家兄弟姐妹多经常挨饿。婚后因为他丈夫王吉生是村官，生活过得去，可能是村里唯一在食堂期间怀孕的妇女。
  - Baiyunqiao Village | 常德市石门县白云乡白云桥村, 2010
    Baiyunqiao Village is located in Shimen County, Changde City, Hunan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Jia Zhitan.
    白云桥村位于湖南省常德市石门县白云乡。村民的录像采访人是贾之坦。
    - Long Tianjian | 龙天建, 2010
      Long Tianjian (b. 1934), the third uncle of the interviewer, Jia Zhitan, is a resident of Baiyuanqiao Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Long talks about three fellow villagers, who died of starvation, and his father, who was beaten to death for stealing the people's commune canteen's grains. Long also recalls how every household's cooking pots were confiscated for constructing blast furnace, and how some villagers were beaten by the leaders for eating too much or too early when participating in the project of Heping Reservoir during the Great Leap Forward.
      龙天建（1934年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡白云桥村村民，是采访者——贾之坦——的三舅。在这段口述中，龙老人讲述了兴办食堂时村里饿死的三位村民，以及自己父亲因为偷公社的谷子被打死的情况。龙老人还回忆了大跃进时期没收各家各户的锅以大炼钢铁，以及1959年修和平水库时有村民因为多吃饭或早吃饭挨干部打的情况。
    - Long Xinye | 龙心叶, 2010
      Long Xinye (b. 1944) is a resident of Baiyunqiao Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Long recounted in detail how he obtained more food in the people's commune canteen with counterfeit food coupons made by himself. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      龙心叶（1944年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡白云桥村村民。在这段口述中，龙老人详细讲述了自己用六两的饭票伪造一斤的饭票、去公社食堂多领饭的过程。
  - Shixiangkou Village | 常德市石门县白云乡石巷口村, 2010
    Shixiangkou Village is located in Shimen County, Changde City, Hunan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Jia Zhitan.
    石巷口村位于湖南省常德市石门县白云乡。村民的录像采访人是贾之坦。
    - Li Yinzhen | 李银珍, 2010
      Li Yinzhen (b. 1944) is a resident of Zhuxiangkou Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Li recalls that her family suffered from hunger when eating at the people's commune canteen, and thus her father died, her mother went blind, and one of her sisters die of smallpox. Li also talks about some villagers, who escaped from the reservoir construction site because of starvation. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      李银珍（1944年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡竹巷口村村民。在这段口述中，李老人回忆兴办公社食堂时期，自己还未出嫁，全家姐妹七人和父母一起挨饿，结果父亲病逝，一个妹妹得天花去世，母亲因病失明。李老人还讲述了修水库的村民因为挨饿偷跑回家的情况。
  - Shuixiyu Village | 常德市石门县白云乡水溪峪村, 2010
    Shuixiyu Village is located in Shimen County, Changde City, Hunan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Jia Zhitan.
    水溪峪村位于湖南省常德市石门县白云乡。村民的录像采访人是贾之坦。
    - Deng Mingxin | 邓明欣, 2010
      Deng Mingxin (b. 1933) is a resident of Shuixiyu Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Deng recalls how people were so hungry during the Great Famine that they ate pig food, and how he went to his aunt's house to seek for food.
      邓明欣（1933年生）湖南省石门县白云乡水溪峪村村民。在这段口述中，邓老人回忆了大饥荒时期人们饿到偷猪食吃的情况，以及他到他姑姑家找吃的一些故事。
  - Wangjiayan Village | 常德市石门县白云乡王家堰村, 2010-2011
    Wangjiayan Village is located in Shimen County, Changde City, Hunan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Jia Zhitan.
    王家堰村位于湖南省常德市石门县白云乡。村民的录像采访人是贾之坦。
    - Chen Xiangzhen | 陈香珍, 2010
      Chen Xiangzhen (b. 1940) is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Chen tells the story of a couple in her village during the Great Famine. To save more food coupons for her husband, the sick wife asked the husband to drown her in a river. But after his wife's death the husband committed suicide by hanging.
      陈香珍（1940年生）湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民。在这段口述中，陈老人回忆了同村另一对老人在大饥荒年间因为粮食紧张，病重的老婆让老伴把自己推到河里淹死，老伴后来上吊自杀的惨剧。
    - Zhao Yongyao | 赵永耀, 2010
      Zhao Yongyao (b. 1929), who worked as the leader of the production team, is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Wang recalls how he led the "sister group" to conduct farming experiment, how 95% of the reservoir workers had been tied and beaten, and how the bone of some villagers' ancestors were digged out of tombs and then were boiled to make farming fertilizer. Zhao estimates that 18 villagers died of starvation when running the people's commune canteen. Zhao also mentions that few babies were born during 1958 and 1961. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      赵永耀（1929年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民，曾担任生产队干部。在这段口述中，赵老人讲述了自己在大跃进期间率领"姐妹队"进行种田实验，修和平水库的百分之九十五的人都遭捆打，为了提高农田产量打狗挖坟、熬肉和骨头做肥料的情况。赵老人估算村里食堂饿死18个人，另外1958年至1961年期间出生的孩子很少。
    - Wang Jisheng | 王吉生, 2010
      Wang Jisheng (b. 1930) is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. Wang was the communist party leader of the party, so he did not suffer from hunger. In this interview, Wang recalls how village leaders implemented the superior leadership's orders strictly, such as forcing the villagers to work in the field before dawn, digging the dead bodies of villagers' ancestors out of tombs, and so on.
      王吉生（1930年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民。大饥荒年间王老人是村支书，没有挨饿，但是王老人回忆了兴办食堂期间村里严格按照上头指示开展工作（比如天不亮就让村民出工劳动，及挖村民祖坟）的情况。
    - Long Tianyuan | 龙天元, 2010
      Long Tianyuan (b. 1938) is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. She is aunt of the interviewer, Jia Zhitan, and married a man in Wangjiayan Village in 1958. That year, Long carried charcoal for constructing blast furnace during the daytime, and attended the review meeting of the production team at night in 1958. In the winter of 1959, the men villagers stripped to waist and the women villagers only wore summer clothing when constructing the Heping Reservoir. The tombstones of some villagers' ancestors' tombs were used to build roads and the reservoir. Long also talks about several fellow villagers, who died of starvation after the people's commune canteen was established, and one villager, who committed suicide after stealing the canteen's soybeans. Long also recounts in detail how she was afflicted during the Great Leap Forward and the Great Famine because her husband's class status was rich farmer, and how her husband died in a coal mine in 1960. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      龙天元（1938年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民。龙老人是采访者——贾之坦——的姨妈，1958年嫁到王家堰村。在这段口述中，龙老人讲述了1958年大炼钢铁时自己白天挑木炭、晚上参加生产队总结会，1959年冬天男人光着上身、女人穿着单衣修和平水库，以及挖村民祖坟的墓碑修公路和水库的情况。龙老人还谈到了兴办公社食堂时饿死的几位村民，一位偷了食堂的黄豆害怕挨批斗而上吊自杀的村民。龙老人还详细谈到了丈夫家因为阶级成分是富农，在大跃进和大饥荒时期处处受到刁难以及丈夫1960年死在外地煤矿的经历。
    - Liu Renci | 刘仁慈, 2010
      Liu Renci (b. 1938) is a resident of Xuanzhongyu Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Liu recalls how the people's commune canteen did not have enough food, though; the villagers were not allowed to cook in their own house. Liu also talks about how he survived the Great Famine thanks to the stolen food coupons given by an acquaintance.
      刘仁慈（1938年生）湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民。在这段口述中，刘老人回忆了食堂粮食供给不足还不准村民私自开火的故事，以及自己靠熟人偷来的饭票扛过饥荒的情况。
    - Liu Yuzhen | 刘玉珍, 2010
      Liu Yuzhen (b. 1919) is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Liu recalls how her in-laws died of starvation and how some villagers were forced to stand for eating grass seeds when running the people's commune canteen.
      刘玉珍（1919年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民。在这段口述中，刘老人讲述了吃食堂时期自己的公公婆婆挨饿致死，以及有村民吃草籽充饥被罚站的情况。
    - Yan Daru | 晏大如, 2010
      Yan Daru (b. 1928) is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Yan recalls how people stripped to waist to build the Heping Reservoir, and how the lazy villager were punished by the production team leaders to kneel on the urine bucket.
      晏大如（1928年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民。在这段口述中，晏老人讲述了1959年修和平水库时号召光着上身劳动，干活偷懒的村民被生产队干部罚跪尿桶的情况。
    - Tang Xishu | 唐西树, 2010
      Tang Xishu (b. 1950) is a resident of Jimingqiao Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Tang recalls his father, who was beaten for being reluctant to join the mutual aid team, and his older brother, who committed suicide because he was reproached by the production team leader for selling wild herb to road workers. Tang also talks about a peer villager, who died of starvation with his eyes open. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      唐西树（1950年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡鸡鸣桥村村民。在这段口述中，唐老人讲述了自己父亲因为不愿意入互助合作社被批斗殴打，自己哥哥1958年挖野菜卖给修公路的人、被生产队干部斥责后上吊自杀的情况。唐老人还谈到了一位饿死后不瞑目的同龄人。
    - Wang Fuying | 王福英, 2010
      Wang Fuying (b. 1929) is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Wang recalls how her house was hardly pulled out to build a pig farm after the people's commune canteen was established. Wang also talks about how the bones of some villagers' ancestors were digged out of tombs to make farming fertilizers.
      王福英（1929年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民。在这段口述中，王老人回忆了兴办公社食堂期间，自己家房子差点被拆了盖猪场的故事，以及村里人挖坟用死人做肥料的情况。
    - Wang Hongying | 王宏英, 2010
      Wang Hongying (b. 1932) is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Wang recalls how her family was bullied and criticized (eg. the bones of their ancestors were digged out of tombs to make farming fertilizers) by the local leaders and fellow villagers because of their class status.
      王宏英（1932年生）湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民。在这段口述中，王老人回忆了大饥荒时期王老人家因为阶级成分被村民和村干部欺压、批斗（比如，家里人的祖坟被挖了做肥料）的情况。
    - Yang Qiuzhen | 杨求珍, 2010
      Yang Qiuzhen (b. 1932) is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Yang recalls how she and her husband were bullied by the local leaders after the people's commune canteen was established while she made every effort to resist the oppression. Yang also recounts how her family survived the famine because of the vegetables she stole from the canteen. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      杨求珍（1932年生）湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民。在这段口述中，杨老人回忆了兴办食堂期间杨老人自己及丈夫受干部欺压，而她一直据理力争反抗干部的的情况。杨老人同时回忆了当年偷食堂的菜回家才让全家免于被饿死的情况。
    - Yang Guangyue | 杨广月, 2010
      Yang Guangyue (b. 1928) is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. Yang married a man in Wangjiayan Village in 1954. Her parents' class status was landlord, and her in-laws' was rich peasant. In this interview, Yang recalls how the people's commune canteen had adequate food supplies at the beginning and later lacked food. At this time the local leaders forbid villagers from eating wild herbs and tree bark because this would bring shame on the commune canteen. Because of complaining about the production team demolishing their house, Yang was punished to kneel and her father-in-law was criticised to death. In 1959, Yang was punished to run with a wooden horse on her back for refusing to join the "sister group" of the production team. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      杨广月（1928年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民。她1954年嫁到该村，自己娘家的阶级成分是地主，丈夫家的阶级成分是富农。在这段口述中，杨老人讲述了1958年兴办公社食堂一开始食物充足、后面食物匮乏时干部不允许村民吃野菜、树皮等充饥，因为这是给食堂抹黑。该时期生产队拆掉杨老人家的房屋、杨老人抱怨被罚跪，公公被批斗致死。1959年杨老人因为不愿意参加生产队的"姊妹队"，被罚背着木马跑步。
    - Chen Anquan | 陈安全, 2010
      Chen Anquan (b. 1933) is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. Chen married a man in Wangjiayan Village in 1933. In this interview, Chen recalls how her in-laws' family were often criticized because their class status was landlord after the people's commune canteen was established. Chen also recounts how her mother-in-law died after being criticized for taking the canteen's turnips back home for Chen, who was pregnant then.
      陈安全（1933年生）湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民。她1947年嫁到该村。在这段口述中，陈老人回忆了大饥荒年间，陈家因为地主成分被批斗，陈老人的婆婆因为从食堂带萝卜回家给怀孕的陈老人吃而被批斗致死的情况。
    - Peng Gongying | 彭功英, 2010
      Peng Gongying (b. 1938) is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In 1957 Peng married Wang Jisheng, who was the leader of Wangjiangyan Village. In this interview, Peng recalls how Zhao, the production team leader, beat a villager for stealing rice from the people's commune canteen.
      彭功英（1938年）是湖南省石门县白云乡王家堰村村民。彭老人1957年嫁到王家堰村，丈夫曾——王吉生——曾担任村支书。在这段口述中，彭老人讲述了生产队队长——赵＊＊——毒打一个偷食堂的米的村民的情况。
    - Liu Bocheng | 刘伯成, 2011
      Liu Bocheng (b. 1932) is a resident of Wangjiayan Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Liu recounts his experience of being labeled as one member of a counter-revolutionary group during the Cultural Revolution because he had a close relationship with the communist party leader of the production team, who had been labeled as a counter-revolutionary. At first Liu was captured, interrogated, and criticized in a school with the other counter-revolutionaries. Later he was jailed in the Police Department of the county for one year until he was rehabilitated in 1971. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      刘伯成（1923年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡王堰村村民。在这段口述中，刘老人回忆了文革期间，自己因为和被打为反革命的大队支书关系好而被打成"反革命集团"一员的故事。刘老人一开始被其他"反革命"一起被关在学校受审，被群众批斗，后来被关到公安局，直到一年后（1971年）平反才被放了出来。
  - Xuanzhongyu Village | 常德市白门县白云乡悬中峪村, 2010
    Xuanzhongyu Village is located in Shimen County, Changde City, Hunan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Jia Zhitan.
    悬钟峪村位于湖南省常德市石门县白云乡。村民的录像采访人是贾之坦。
    - Zhao Yuanyun | 赵远云, 2010
      Zhao Yuanyun (b. 1950) is a resident of Xuanzhongyu Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Zhao recounted how his classmate, Zhao, attempted suicide several times because he was often criticized for his landlord class status.
      赵远云（1950年生）湖南省石门县白云乡悬中峪村村民。在这段口述中，赵老人回忆了同村的董学元因地主身份挨整几次试图自杀的故事。
    - Xiao Kaihua | 肖开化, 2010
      Xiao Kaihua (b. 1929) is a resident of Xuanzhongyu Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Xiao recalls how he survived the Great Famine because he served the production team with his tailoring skills. Xiao also talks about an old man, who passed out because of hunger, and the hungry wild jackals, which came to the village to eat children. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      肖开化（1929年生）湖南省石门县白云乡水悬钟峪村村民。在这段口述中，肖老人讲述了自己利裁缝手艺为生产队服务，所以在饥荒年间没有挨饿的故事。肖老人还回忆了该时期村里老人饿死，村外豺狼饿极进村叼小孩的情况。
    - Xiang Ma | 项妈, 2010
      Xiang Ma (b. 1937) is a resident of Xuanzhongyu Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Xiang Ma recalls how she ate the bark of loquat tree during the Great Famine, and how she did not have enough money to treat her daughter's arthritis, which resulted in a sequela.
      项妈（1937年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡水悬钟峪村村民。在这段口述中，项妈回忆了大饥荒年间吃枇杷树皮充饥，以及女儿关节炎没钱买药留下后遗症的情况。
    - Xiao Kaihan | 肖开汉, 2010
      Xiao Kaihan (b. 1932) is a resident of Xuanzhongyu Village, Baiyun Town, Shimen County, Hunan Province. Xiao worked as a commander of the local people's militia and the security director of the production team. In this interview, Xiao recounts how two other security leaders tied and beat production team members who worked for the project of Heping Reservoir in the winter of 1959. In the contrary, Xiao recounts how he himself took advantage of his position to save three villagers, who snatched or stole food to eat. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      肖开汉（1932年生）是湖南省石门县白云乡悬钟峪村村民。肖老人1957年从部队复员回家，担任生产队的民办营长兼治保主任。在这段口述中，肖老人介绍1959年冬修和平水库时，负责治安的另外两名干部经常捆绑吊打劳动的社员。但肖老人讲述了自己凭借职务之便，救了三位抢饭或偷饭吃的村民的故事。
  - Datang Village | 怀化市溆浦县双井镇大塘村, 2010-2011
    Datang Village is located in Xupu County, Huaihua City, Hunan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and flimed by Shu Qiao.
    大塘村位于湖南省怀化市溆浦县双井镇。村民的录像采访人是舒侨。
    - Liu Jinchan | 刘金蝉, 2010-2011
    - Xiang Jianshu | 向建树, 2010-2011
  - Huakou Village | 怀化市溆浦县双井镇化口村, 2012
    Huakou Village is located in Xupu County, Huaihua City, Hunan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and flimed by Shu Qiao.
    化口村位于湖南省怀化市溆浦县双井镇。村民的录像采访人是舒侨。
    - Xiang Layun | 向腊云, 2012
      Xiang Layun (b.1930) is a resident of Huakou Village, Shuangjing Town, Xupu County, Huaihua City, Hunan Province. In this interview, Xiang recalls life during Land Reform and Great Famine. For the Land Reform they struggled the landlords and confiscated their properties, and each person in her family was distributed one mu of land. When People's Communal canteen started, people could eat as much as they liked, but later food supply became limited and was not enough. The Production Team stole food collectively and distributed to each family, so not many people starved to death.
      向腊云1930年出生，是湖南省怀化市溆浦县双井镇化口村的村民。在这段口述中，向老人回忆了土改以及大饥荒时期的生活。土改时打地主，抄地主的家，她家每个人都分到了一亩地。开始吃食堂的时候随便吃，后来发定粮不够吃，队里统一去偷粮食分给每家人，所以他们没怎么饿死人。
  - Shuangjing Village | 怀化市溆浦县双井镇双井村, 2010-2012
    Shuangjing Village is located in Xupu County, Huaihua City, Hunan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and flimed by Shu Qiao.
    双井村位于湖南省怀化市溆浦县双井镇。村民的录像采访人是舒侨。
    - Xiang Debi | 项德碧, 2011
    - Shu Yusong | 舒煜松, 2012
    - Li Meiying | 李美英, 2010-2012
    - Zhang Ziying | 张滋英, 2010-2011
    - Yi Weiying | 易卫英, 2012
    - Xie Lide | 谢历德, 2011
      Xie Lide (b.1946) is a resident of Shuangjing Village, Shuangjing Town, Xupu County, Huaihua City, Hunan Province. He is Luo Yunbi's husband. In this interview, Xie talks about experiences during the Great Famine and Cultural Revolution. Helong meal began in 1958, he was in the fifth grade and only had six liang of food every day; not able to get full, he always ate sugar canes in the farm. He also remembers all kinds of food back then, people who died in the Production Team, and how they exchanged food from people in the mountainous areas with worn-out clothes and even daughters' marriages. During the Cultural Revolution he was in the army in Yantai, Shandong Province, and experienced class struggles every day. He especially cannot forget the incident of power seizure by the red guards that took place in 1967. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      谢历德1946年出生，是湖南省怀化市溆浦县双井镇双井村的村民。他是罗运碧的丈夫。在这段口述中，谢老人讲述了大饥荒以及文化大革命时期的经历。1958年开始吃合拢饭，上小学五年级的他每天只有六两米饭，成天吃不饱，到地里用甘蔗充饥。他也回忆了当时的各种食物，队里死的人，以及用破衣服甚至嫁女儿的方法和山里人换吃的的情况。文革时期他在烟台当兵，每天都经历这阶级斗争。他尤其难忘1967年在那发生的红卫兵夺权事件。
    - Xie Yusui | 谢玉穗, 2010
      Xie Yusui (b. 1939) was born in Shuangjing Village, Shuangjing Town, Xupu County, Huaihua City, Hunan Province. In this interview, Xie describes the difficulties since the beginning of the Great Leap Forward. Due to food shortage, people stole from the farm, the mountain or vegetable gardens. Later on, they carried coal for People's Commune Canteen from Haicongwan everyday. After 1960 when people began eating at the canteen, three people in her family (father, aunt, uncle) died, and so did many others living in her courtyard. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      谢玉穗1939年出生于湖南省怀化市溆浦县双井镇双井村。在这段口述中，谢老人 讲述了大跃进开始后的辛苦。因为没有食物，人们去田里，山上或者菜园里偷食。后来他们每天帮食堂到害丛湾挑煤炭。1960年吃大食堂饭后，她的家里饿死了三口人（父亲，伯母，伯伯），同时院子里也死了好多。
    - Zhang Peiying | 张佩英, 2012
    - Zhang Chunsheng | 张春生, 2010
    - Shu Youying | 舒友英, 2012
      Shu Youying (b.1940) is a resident of Shuangjing Village, Shuangjing Town, Xupu County, Huaihua City, Hunan Province. In this interview, Shu remembers life during the Great Famine. When eating at People's Commune canteen, she helped looking after the children at the Production Team, and had 4 liang of rice every day. Her father who worked at the canteen ate meat of dead pig and died of sickness.
      舒友英1940年出生，是湖南省怀化市溆浦县双井镇双井村的村民。在这段口述中，舒老人回忆了大饥荒期间的生活。吃食堂的时候，她在队里帮带孩子，一天4两米。当时在食堂做事的父亲吃了死猪肉之后病死了。
    - Shu Yulin | 舒煜林, 2010-2012
    - Shu Boan | 舒伯安, 2012
    - Zhang Guixiu | 张贵休, 2010
      Zhang Guixiu (b. 1933) is a resident of Shuangjing Village, Shuangjing Town, Xupu County, Huaihua City, Hunan Province. In this interview, Zhang recalls her experience during the Great Leap Forward. Back then, she saved the food from the People's Commune canteen and what she found from outside for her children. If she went out working, the children would be left at home by themselves. One time, she carried her little son (who has died of illness) to the field when she was sick. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      张贵休1933年出生，是湖南省怀化市溆浦县双井镇双井村的村民。在这段口述中，张老人回忆了大饥荒期间的经历。那时，她把食堂的饭和外面找来的野菜都留给孩子们吃。出去干活时家里的孩子就没人照看。有一次她生病还把小儿子（已病故）背着去耕田。
    - Liu Qiuzhi | 刘秋芝, 2012
    - Liu Qunqing | 刘群庆, 2011
    - Shu Qingyou | 舒清友, 2010-2011
      Shu Qingyou (b.1930) is a resident of Shuangjing Village, Shuangjing Town, Xupu County, Huaihua City, Hunan Province. In this interview, Shu recalls experiences during the Land Reform, Great Leap Forward, and Great Famine. When Land Reform began in 1950, he was the squadron leader of the militiamen and was in charge of the military equipment; together with the new team, he criticized the landlords and divided their possessions. During the Great Leap Forward, the yield was falsely reported as a result of proneness to boasting and exaggeration. He remembers that some one made a complaint and was then critized on the same night. Later there was no food when eating at the People's Communal canteen, the Commune members ate secretly while the cadres snatched the food, and the ordinary folks also stole everywhere. Many people got the edema disease, and those almost starving to death were sent to the elder's home for treatment, most of who died as well.
      舒清友1930年出生，是湖南省怀化市溆浦县双井镇双井村的村民。在这段口述中，舒老人回忆了土改，大跃进以及大饥荒期间的经历。1950年土改开始后，他是民兵中队长，负责管武装，和新班子一起清算地主、分财产。大跃进时因为浮夸风都虚报产量。他记得有人发了句牢骚晚上就被批斗了。后来吃食堂没有粮食，社员偷着吃干部抢着吃，老百姓也四处去偷。很多人得了水肿病，快饿死的人都被送到养老院去调养，但大部分也都死了。
    - Shu Qingliang | 舒清亮, 2011
      Shu Qingliang (b.1941) is a resident of Shuangjing Village, Shuangjing Town, Xupu County, Huaihua City, Hunan Province. In this interview, Shu remembers life during the Great Leap Forward and Great Famine. His narration covers experiences such as People's Commune, constructing blast furnace, and struggle sessions. Speaking of starvation, he believes that peasants lacked autonomy then and must submit to unreasonable decisions made by the Production Team. Fortunately, he was working at a sugar factory and gained nutrition from sugar canes. The filmmaker's description of this interview has been translated into English.
      舒清亮1941年出生，是湖南省怀化市溆浦县双井镇双井村的村民。在这段口述中，舒老人回忆了大跃进和大饥荒期间的生活。他讲述了人民公社，大炼钢铁，以及批斗等大跃进的经历。说起挨饿的苦日子，他认为农民没有自主，必须服从生产队不合理的决定。幸运的是，当时在糖厂工作的他靠甘蔗补充了营养。
    - Zhang Huaqing | 张华清, 2011
    - Shu Caili | 舒采礼, 2011
      Shu Caili (b.1933) is a resident of Shuangjing Village, Shuangjing Town, Xupu County, Huaihua City, Hunan Province. In this interview, He remembers life during the Great Famine. He passed away in early 2012.
      舒采礼1933年出生，是湖南省怀化市溆浦县双井镇双井村的村民。在这段口述中，舒老人回忆了大饥荒期间的生活。舒老人2012年初过世。
    - Shu Qingfu | 舒清福, 2012
    - Xiang Guixiang | 向桂香, 2011
    - YANG Fenghua | 杨凤华, 2011
    - Luo Yunbi | 罗运碧, 2011